It sounds too simple, just taking
vitamin C and effectively stressing and
killing cancer cells. But there is some
powerful science behind that claim,
especially when paired with a particular
short, key word there, nutrition
protocol. So, what does a massive study
indicate about vitamin C? An extremely
surprising mechanism by which it works,
how it only works in the right
circumstances, and of course, what is
this nutrition protocol? I'm talking
about breathtakingly fascinating data
coming from this study where researchers
used a nutrition protocol called a
fasting mimicking diet alone or with
vitamin C to see what happens to cancer
cells. At first they started out by
simply using isolated human cancer cells
here. Here we're looking at a measure of
cell death, a good thing in this
context. So the higher the bars, the
more cancer cells are dying. The CTR
condition is the normal conditions of
the cancer cells. The STS is a condition
designed to mimic the fasting mimicking
diet. A lot of mimicking going around.
And the final two conditions are the
same but with vitamin C added. As we can
see, both the vitamin C conditions led
to a greater cancer cell death. But look
at the far right condition. The
nutrition protocol condition plus
vitamin C led to a near 100%
annihilation
of the cancer cells. Fascinatingly, they
were able to repeat these results in
multiple other cancers from colorectal
cancers to lung cancers to pancreatic
cancers all with the same effect.
However, there is a huge mystery that
came forward quite soon afterwards
because when they did the exact same
experiments on other cancers, there was
no effect. no cancer death. And the
kicker, these cancer cells were also
colurectal cancer cells. So wait,
vitamin C and fasting mimicking diet
kill cancer cells, but then when they're
used against other cancer cells from the
same cancer area like the colon, there's
no effect. Something is missing that
doesn't square, right? The answer lies
in a specific mutation that the cancers
although they come from the same place
do not share. The cancer cells that do
experience mass death have a krass
mutation while the insensitive ones do
not. So to recap, the fasting mimicking
diet plus vitamin C kills all these
cancer cells but only if they have a
specific mutation. We'll discuss which
cancers in a bit. Now, I'm not going to
bore you with what Krass mutation is
because it doesn't help us to understand
the rest of what we're about to uncover.
Just know it's a problem in our genes
and it makes cancer susceptible to
vitamin C. But up to now, we've been
looking at isolated cells. It's easy to
destroy cancer cells when you remove
them from their environment, your body.
So, do these results remain when looking
at cancer in the body? The answer is
yes. You can look at either graph. They
show similar results. The takeaway here
is the blue line, the blue condition is
lower than the other conditions. And
since we're measuring tumor size, that's
definitely a good thing. These data are
in mice. And the researchers are using a
closerto reality fasting mimicking diet.
But even so, I can tell you some of this
has also been shown to be true in
humans. All right. Remarkable results
across multiple experiments. Cancer
cells with a Krass mutation are severely
damaged without harm to healthy cells,
mind you, by a fasting mimicking diet
paired with vitamin C. But here's where
I was pretty stunned by the results. Not
to say that the information that we just
went over wasn't already incredible. How
does vitamin C have these cancer killing
effects? At first, you might, like me,
think that vitamin C might be working
through its potent antioxidant
abilities. For those unaware, that means
that vitamin C can interact with
potentially harmful oxidizing molecules
like reactive oxygen species, which
interact with the structure of our cells
and damage them. When vitamin C and
other antioxidants interact with these
oxidants, they neutralize them, making
them less reactive and dangerous.
Vitamin C is known to be a potent
antioxidant. But check this out. No,
vitamin C not only doesn't work through
its antioxidant mechanism, but it
massively increases the oxidative
stress, more destructive oxidant
molecules in the cancer cells. This is
wild. So, the takeaway here is that
vitamin C does still massively hurt
cancer cells, but not through typical
means. It actually acts through a
completely non-intuitive mechanism by
increasing damaging oxidizing molecules
within cancer cells. And as a final nail
in the coffin, the researchers also
discovered that vitamin C reduces the
amount of a protective protein in the
cancer cells. That protective protein is
called feritin heavy chain and it grabs
onto iron molecules. That's important
because iron can be very dangerous if
it's free inside the cell because the
free iron will interact with the
structure of the cell and damage it
because iron is highly oxidizing in its
bound state is not as reactive in the
same way. So imagine what's happening in
the cancer cells when there's less of
this protective binding protein and much
greater concentration of free iron. Mass
havoc. In fact, people with Kass
mutation cancers live longer if they
also have low expression of this
protective ironbinding protein. Again,
translating this association to humans.
Okay, so there's a lot here, but we can
sum it up in two simple points before
getting to the action actionable steps.
One, Krass mutant cancers suffer
dreadfully when exposed to a fasting
mimicking diet and vitamin C. Two,
vitamin C increases rather than
decreases destructive oxidizing
molecules within the cancer, likely by
reducing the amount of a protective
ironbinding protein. Now, how should we
think about all this? Well, this is all
pre-clinical research, right? As in,
we've been looking at cells and animals.
And although you're made of cells, and
you are an animal, you beast, you, it
isn't good enough to translate this
directly to humans. And more
unfortunate, there are no clinical
trials using vitamin C and fasting
mimicking dieting. So, did I waste our
time here? I actually haven't for
multiple reasons. one, there is a
clinical trial in the works using these
exact strategies. I will certainly be
covering it regardless of the result
when it releases. So stay tuned for
that. Two, there are clinical trials
looking at vitamin C without fasting
mimicking diet. And although the overall
study indicates no benefit, we actually
suspect that to be the case because
we're only focused on Krass mutant
cancers. And when looking at only Krass
mutant cancers, there is a benefit of
vitamin C. And three, we have studies on
fasting mimicking diet showing improved
cancer outcomes. So yes, we need more
studies, but the horizon looks quite
promising. I will also point out
directly that all these studies except
for the main one that we've been over
has paired vitamin C or fasting
mimicking diet with the usual doctor's
care. So I don't want you thinking that
this is an eitheror scenario. In fact,
in our main study, the researchers did
further experiments pairing the fasting
mimicking diet with vitamin C, but also
added a usual anti-cancer drug. And they
showed even greater effectiveness than
when doing without. Okay, all that said,
how do we apply this? Now, I'm going to
walk you through how the researchers do
it. And if you're interested in a more
tailored detailed breakdown, I have a
personalized calculator and a written
protocol available along with much more
on Krass mutation and odd effect of an
acetylcyine. So knack potent antioxidant
and more specifics on the mechanisms
that we went over in this video. All of
that is included for the physionic
insiders, my premium research platform
that comes with all these other perks
too. If you're interested, check it out
in the description box. I would love to
have you join. Now, a fasting mimicking
diet, which will now be abbreviated FMD,
works like this. It's a nutrition
protocol that lasts only 5 days, hence
the easy in the title of the video. You
would drop your calorie consumption to
600 calories on day one. Then for the
next 4 days, you would consume a mere
300 calories per day. Then the
macronutrient breakdown is a low
protein, moderate to high carbohydrate
and fat nutrition sitting around 10%
protein, 45% carbohydrates, and 45%
dietary fat. You would do this once per
month every month. In addition, the
original FMD uses a plant-based
nutrition. Now, I realize some will
recoil and hiss
like a cat dowsed in water, but that's
what the studies used, so take it up
with them. As the as for the vitamin C,
the studies use very high doses, many
grams of vitamin C. But be aware that
consuming many grams of vitamin C can
cause GI distress, kidney stones, and in
some high iron absorbers increase iron
absorption as well as mess with routine
blood tests. So while more mild than
some other vitamins in high doses, still
be cautious. So overall, how do we sum
this neatly? The main study that we went
over indicates that vitamin C paired
with a fasting mimicking diet stresses
and kills cancer cells that are Krass
mutant cancers. So some examples of
Krass mutant cancers are colurectal
adenino cararcinomomas,
pancreatic ductal adino carcinomaomas,
uh small intestinal adino carcinomaomas,
lung adenino cararcinomomas, ovarian
cancers,
and there's several others, but uh these
are among the most common. I need to
stress here that not all cancers are
Krass mutant cancer. So the best course
of action is to step one ask about your
cancer and discuss with your physician.
Step two, if it is a krass mutant
cancer, discuss with your physician if
there are other reasons excluding you
from trying a fasting mimicking diet.
Step three, if you can do a fasting
mimicking diet, prior prioritize your
vitamin C consumption as well. But keep
in mind that we don't have hard clinical
data on the combination yet in spite of
all that we just went over. And step
four, probably the most important step
of them all,
educate yourself further on your health
by watching this next video. I'll catch
you over there. I mean, I will literally
chase after you and tickle you.